<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A most straunge, and true discourse, of the wonderfull iudgement of God. Of a monstrous, deformed infant, begotten by incestuous copulation, betweene the brothers sonne and the sisters daughter, being both vnmarried persons. Which childe was borne at Colwall, in the country and diocesse of Hereford, vpon the sixt day of Ianuary last, being the feast of the Epiphany, commonly called Twelfth day. A notable and most terrible example against incest and whoredome.</title>
            <title>Most straunge, and true discourse, of the wonderfull judgement of God</title>
            <author>I. R., fl. 1600.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1600</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10292</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20575</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106049</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841774</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841774</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6380</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10292)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6380)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1608:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A most straunge, and true discourse, of the wonderfull iudgement of God. Of a monstrous, deformed infant, begotten by incestuous copulation, betweene the brothers sonne and the sisters daughter, being both vnmarried persons. Which childe was borne at Colwall, in the country and diocesse of Hereford, vpon the sixt day of Ianuary last, being the feast of the Epiphany, commonly called Twelfth day. A notable and most terrible example against incest and whoredome.</title>
                  <title>Most straunge, and true discourse, of the wonderfull judgement of God</title>
                  <author>I. R., fl. 1600.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By E. Allde] for Richard Iones,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1600.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The epistle to the reader" signed: R.I.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signature A2 missigned A3.</note>
                  <note>Some pages stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Incest --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Abnormalities, Human --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6380:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6380:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Moſt ſtraunge, and true diſcourſe, of the wonderfull <hi>iudgement of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>OF A MONSTROVS, DEFOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Infant, begotten by inceſtuous co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulation, betweene the brothers ſonne and the ſiſters daughter, being both vnmarried perſons.</p>
            <p>Which childe was borne at <hi>Colwall,</hi> in the County and Dioceſſe of <hi>Hereford,</hi> vpon the ſixt day of <hi>Ianuary</hi> laſt, being the feaſt of the <hi>Epiphany,</hi> commonly called Twelfth day. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>599.</p>
            <p>A notable and moſt terrible example againſt Inceſt, and Whoredome.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at LONDON, for <hi>Richard Iones.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:6380:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6380:2"/>
            <head>TO THE GODLY REA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, I.R. wiſheth health &amp; holineſſe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood Reader, when this matter was brought vnto me, to conſider of, that it might be drawne into forme for the Printers preſſe, I was partly vnwilling to meddle with it: for as much as I know, that the ſinnes of Inceſt, Onaniſme, Whoredome, Adulterie &amp; Forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, with other Sodomiticall ſinnes of vnclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe &amp; pollutions, do ſo outragiouſly raign, and are in theſe dayes ſo much vſed in many places, with ouer-much bouldneſſe and preſumption, for lack of ſharpe &amp; due puniſhment for the ſame: and that ſuch haynous and great crimes &amp; abuſes had neede to be throughly handled, &amp; ſpoken of, by ſome moſt worthy man, of farre greater giftes and learning, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my ſelfe am; the better to pearce the obdurate &amp; ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny heartes of great numbers, that are therewith gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly infected; and to diſſwade others from falling thereinto.</p>
            <p>Yet being willing to do my countrie good, and to make ſome vſe of my poore talent in this behalfe, &amp; being importuned by often entreaties of ſome my friends, vnto whom I could not well denie any reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable requeſt, who aſſured me that the report there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was deliuered them in writing, by a gentleman of good credite &amp; worſhip, in the countie of <hi>Hereford,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:6380:3"/>&amp; neare to the place wher this hapned: I thought it my part, for the benefit of others, to do what I might herein; &amp;, as I truſt, for the good of many, &amp; hurte of none, as breefely &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly as mought be, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it in ſo ſmal a treatiſe, as this is. Wherfore (good Reader) accept thereof, as of a ſimple admonitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: that this noble Realme, wherein we liue, may not be ſo polluted and defiled, as it is: but that more prayer, faſting, and reſtraint of fleſhly luſtes and deſires, with more diligent reading and hearing of the ſcriptures, may be vſed: whereby thoſe haynous ſinnes, may the better be bridled and auoided in euerie one of vs. And eſpecially, that the ſame breake not out, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſo great outrage, as it doeth, and hath done of late yeares: whereby god is ſo highly diſhonoured, that by the groſſe iniquitie of the people, he is prouoked to ſend ſuch monſters, for part of puniſhment vpon vs, into the world, that may make vs aſhamed of our ſelues, and the readyer to hate &amp; deteſt ſinne, and by all due meanes, to ſeeke ſeuere puniſhment for the ſame (without partiality) on ſuch perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, as therin fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> time to time ſhal offend. For which purpoſe, all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, who haue authoritie to puniſh the ſame, ought to be carefull, that too many offences of that kind be not redeemed by commutations: leaſt it come to paſſe that there ſhould be much more money payd to buy out ſinne, then perſons puniſhed for ſinne: whereby it might be doubted, whither we may ſay, as maſter <hi>Latymer</hi> ſaid once in a ſermon, that ſin is good marcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>diſe, in many Courts &amp; Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtories. Which, if it ſhould be ſo, the Lord in his
<pb facs="tcp:6380:3"/>good time redreſſe it, in them that vſe it. For by this meanes, as god is diſhonoured, ſo, the Queenes maieſtie and her gouernement, the preachers of the Goſpell and their teaching, are ſlaundered and euill ſpoken of, by Papiſts, Browniſts, and others, both abroade and at home. Who, not rightly conſidering that the multitude of the people breedeth ſinne, and that towards the latter dayes, iniquitie ſhall increaſe, do ſlaunderouſly ſpeake of vs, contrarie to the truth. Now, here followeth a deſcription of all things, whereby thou mayſt be fully ſatisfied, how, when, and where, this ſtrange thing was done: with euery other circumſtance thereto belonging. Laſtly, here is an earneſt admonition to withdrawe people from the ſinnes of Whoredome &amp; vnclea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neſſe: ſuch as I hope ſhall doe much good, &amp; preuaile with ſome, amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt many, that liue wickedly in theſe dayes. Such as it is, I do now at this time conueigh into thy hands, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting thee, &amp; all that looke for ſaluation in Chriſt Ieſus, to the bleſſed tuition of the moſt mightie: who ſayth, <hi>Be ye holy, for I am holie.</hi> From my houſe, this 30. of Aprill. 1600.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>The Lords vnworthy ſeruant, and thine, <hi>I. R.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:6380:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6380:4"/>
            <head>A TRVE DESCRIPTION of a ſtraunge monſter, borne at <hi>Colwall,</hi> in <hi>the County of</hi> Hereford. <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T pleaſeth God (who is wonderfull in al his works) to worke wonders, when men liue ſo wonderfully euill, as they doe in this age and time. And although God doth not in ſuch ſeueritie deſtroy his peóple, nowe in the time of mercie and grace, as hee did vnder the lawe, and before (as <hi>Gen. 7.</hi> and the <hi>19. Exod. 16.</hi> the <hi>17.</hi> and <hi>32. Numb. 11.</hi> and the <hi>16. 1. Cor. 10. &amp;c</hi>) yet is he no leſſe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry with ſinne, nor no leſſe powerfull to puniſh ſinne, then in times paſt he hath beene: as it appeareth by the ſundry iudgements that hee ſends, to ſhew the ſame among men: as, plague, peſtilence, warre, famine, ſcarcity, dearth, new ſickneſſes and diſeaſes, Comets, blazing ſtarres, flaſhing lightes, ſhooting and ſtreamings in the ayre, monſters of man and beaſt &amp;c Whereof, this that wee are now to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe, is not the leaſt whereat men may greatly be aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, and afraide to ſinne; if they had any feare of God in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For it is ſo ſtrange a thing, as that neither mans arie can ſet out, nor yet the tongue, or penne of man tell of, as it ought to be ſhewed and ſet out. But as neare as we
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:6380:5"/>can (that haue the handling of it) you ſhall heare and ſee what it was.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The matter it ſelfe.</head>
               <p>THere was a young maiden, a yeomans daughter of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reford</hi> ſhire (whoſe names for ſome cauſes wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale) who had conuenient offers of mariages, fit for her eſtate: and within theſe two yeares laſt paſt, among all the reſt, one young man loued her moſt entirely: who, though hee were none of the braueſt nor iollieſt, yet a man of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent wealth, and of good name and fame in the place where he dwelt. This young man and maiden, in time, loued one another ſo wel (&amp; their friends of either ſide, as it ſhould ſeeme ſo liked thereof) y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> they were contracted toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; openly aſked three times in the Church (or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> banes of matrymony between them publiſhed in the congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) according to the lawe, in that caſe prouided: and all the people of thoſe parts thought for trueth, that a full match in mariage, ſhould ſhortly after haue beene ſolemnized betweene them.</p>
               <p>But Sathan,<note place="margin">Note yee young maidens.</note> the enemie of all goodnes, by his inſtigations and inſtruments, wrought ſo in the minde of the maiden; that ſhortly after this, ſhe fell to miſlike with the man, to ſhunne his honeſt company, and in the ende wholly to breake off from this match: whereof, any maid indewed with modeſty, would haue beene greatly aſhamed, and vnwilling vnto: eſpecially when there was no iuſt cauſe giuen her on the mans part; as right well it was proued there was not.</p>
               <p>But ſuch is the lightneſſe and inconſtancy of a great number of this ſexe, that true meaning men can not tell where to finde them. They are many times in extreames: for, either they will not at all bee ruled by their parentes
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:6380:5"/>and friends, in mariage: but meete by ſtealth, &amp; run away in a night, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him, whom ſo vnaduiſedly they loue: or elſe, when with their parents and friends conſent, they haue aſſured themſelues, and entangled the mindes of younge men; yet vpon ſome ſiniſter cauſe they will flit and fall off againe; yea, and ſometimes get a great bellie by ſome ſuch, match, and ſo breake off, with all the ſhame that may be. In this point, I confeſſe, many young men (thorough the heate and ſtrength of luſt and concupiſence) haue moſt ſhamefully abuſed, both widdowes and maydens,<note place="margin">Note y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> young <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> too too many. But the puniſhment of God doth euer follow ſuch, and at one time or other ſo ouertake them, as that they ſhall be driuen to confeſſe that there is a iuſt God in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, which puniſheth that which men doe neglect to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh in earth.</p>
               <p>But to returne to this monſtrous matter, wee haue in hand: when this ſlipperie Eele had made a ſhift to winde away from this man, in this laſt yeare <hi>1599.</hi> ſhe dwelling as a ſeruant, in the houſe of one of her Vncles by the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſide (at a place called <hi>Mathenne in Worceſter</hi> ſhire) this hir Vncle had three ſonnes at mans eſtate, which were couſen germanes to this mayde.</p>
               <p>Now in tract of time it fell out ſo, that one of theſe yong men, her couſens, and ſhe fell a luſting; for, good loue I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not well call it; partly becauſe hee was hir ſo neere kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man: and partly for that ſhe had promiſed her ſelfe before, to another man: and eſpecially becauſe their luſt was ſo hot, that ſoone after the ſame began to be kindled, it was ſo ſet on fire, and the diuell had ſo blinded the eies of theſe two, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> they lay togither, &amp; ſhee was gotten with child by him: and God in iuſt iudgment (to ſhew his diſpeaſure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt mockerie with his holy inſtitution of mariage, and his hatred of the ſinnes of whoredom, adulterie, fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, inceſte, and all other vncleanneſſe) made this proud,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:6380:6"/>this ſcornefull &amp; vnconſtant wench, the mother of a mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and not of an orderly birth. For when the time of her deliuerance was come, and that ſhe had gon out her full <hi>9.</hi> moneths (as all women doe, that bring not forth vntime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly birthes) ſhee was deliuered of a child, ſuch as it was; and y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> in a houſe of her ſayd Vncles, at <hi>Colwall</hi> afore-na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, the <hi>6.</hi> day of <hi>Ianuarie</hi> laſt paſt, in <hi>Anno, 1599.</hi> And now for the further certifying of thee chriſtian reader, of the miſſhapened forme of this monſtrous birth, and many particularities in ſundrie ſeuerall limbes, members, and partes of the bodie of it, with other ſtrange circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces appertaining thereunto, reade this matter following: which thou ſhalt finde truelie ſet downe word for word, as the ſame was ſeene and taken in writing; at the appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a Gentleman of good crevit and worſhip, in the preſence of diuers honeſt and credible perſons, both men and women.</p>
               <p>There was a young woman, a yeomans daughter, who was offered honeſt preferment in marriage, about two yeares paſt, with a young man of competent wealth and good credit: with whom ſhe proceeded ſo farre that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> banes of holie matrimonie were three ſeuerall dayes, orderly according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Eccleſiaſticall lawes, proclaimed between them. And then ſhe being poſſeſſed with ſome ſiniſter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, brake off with him, without any iuſt occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> giuen on his parte. Afterward, this laſt yeare, ſhe dwelling as a mayde-ſeruant in houſe with an vncle of hers, <hi>viz.</hi> her mothers brother, at <hi>Mathenne,</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Countie &amp; Dioceſſe of <hi>Worceſter:</hi> who then alſo hauing in his houſe three Sonnes of mans eſtate, ſhe was begotten with childe by one of them: and it is credibly reported, that two of them liued incontinently with her, being her coſen ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes. And the competent time of her childebirth appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, vpon the ſaid ſixt day of <hi>Ianuarie, 1599.</hi> ſhee was
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:6380:6"/>deliuered of childe, in a houſe of her ſaide uncles in <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wall,</hi> in the ſaid Countie and Dioceſſe of <hi>Hereford,</hi> about the ſun ſetting of the ſame day: which child was thus diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figured.</p>
               <p n="1">1 The head of it was longer then the heades of other children ordinarily are, hauing neither haire on the head, nor on the eie-browes.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Both the eies were ſtanding far out of the head, being vnequall the one to the other: the right eye verie ſmall, like a blacke ſloe, ſticked halfe out, in the flat face (hauing neither eyelid nor eyepit) as it were a bullet ſlicking in a plaine wall. But the left eye was verie big &amp; eminent, or ſticking out as the other; yet hauing eye-lidds, which were diſtracted and drawne farre aſunder, the vpper eye-lid vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and the lower eye-lidde downewards, the inſides appeering outward.</p>
               <p n="3">3 The noſe was depreſſed flat to the face, without any noſthrills at all; hauing at the lower end therof, arounde button of fleſhie ſubſtance about the bignes of a nut: on eyther ſide whereof, ſomwhat higher then the noſe, the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per lippe was ſlitte or hare-ſhorne: from which twoo ſlitts, throughout the palat or roufe of the mouth, there paſſed 2. hollowe trenches, each one almoſt two fingers deepe, euen to the gullet or entraunce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> throate: which ſeemed to be the paſſage of the noſthrils: and throughout the lower part of the mouth, on eyther ſide of the tongue, was a like deepe trench.</p>
               <p n="4">4 The mouth was much ſmaller, then ordinarily o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther childrens mouthes are, therin appearing no gummes nor iawbones at all, nor any lippes could be diſcerned.</p>
               <p n="5">5 The face much wrinkled and riueled, more then any other childrens faces vſe to bee, and very grimme to behoulde.</p>
               <p n="6">6 The handes had no thumbes at all, nor any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:6380:7"/>partition of fingers; yet it had fingers co<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ered all ouer with one only ſkinne, as with a mitten: the fingers had ioynts as it did appeare, by that it often clitched them together.</p>
               <p n="7">7 The finger of the left hand only (which in latine is called <hi>digitus annularis,</hi> and in engliſh <hi>the ring finger</hi>) had a naile, and that finger towards the end was ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the others.</p>
               <p n="8">8 There appeared in this childe no euident ſigne of the ſexe, either of man or woman, hauing the perfect mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of neither: but vrine iſſued out at a ſmal hole in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per place: of notes for difference, reſembling ſome token more proper to male, then female.</p>
               <p n="9">9 The knees ſtoode vp cloſe to the belly, and the legs were fixed to the buttockes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> calfe of the left legge grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the buttocke, and thigh vnto the ſmall of the legge: but the right legge, quite downe to the heele, within two fingers breadth.</p>
               <p n="10">10 The right foote, almoſt from the midſt therof, bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or turned towardes the left; and with a ſtringe of fleſh was faſt ioyned to the ſame, at the endes of the great toes: which toes withall the reſt of the toes were couered ouer with one entier ſkinne, as the fingers were.</p>
               <p n="11">11 The bodie, for length and bigneſſe, exceeded the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie ſtature of other children. When this woman was firſt deliuered of this monſtrous burden, the Midwiues (being three in number then preſent) thinking it had no life, laid it by on a fewe Bents: where it lay without any couering, halfe an houre; and then it cryed, and not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. And they hearing it cry, tooke it vp and put clothes about it, vſing it as a childe ought to be vſed: &amp;, thinking that it would not liue to be brought to the Church to bee baptized, they ſent for the Miniſter and Paſtour of <hi>Colwall</hi> (within whoſe charge it was borne) to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:6380:7"/>it: who being a zealous man, and a learned Preacher, repaired thither with all ſpeede: and finding by his owne inſpection, and due examination of the perſons preſent at the birth of the ſaide childe, that it was thus ſtraungely formed and figured, and being accompanied with compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent witneſſes, he baptized the ſaid child; naming it, <hi>What god will.</hi> And after it was baptized, it liued two daies and two nights, and more; and the third day it departed this life. And during the time it liued, it receiued ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and had euacuation of naturall ſuperfluities, both by vrine, &amp; ſiege: but in all that time it was not perceiued to ſleepe: and in trueth it could not bee diſcerned to cloſe the eyes, becauſe it had no eyeliddes to couer them.</p>
               <p>Thus haue you heard the wonderfull deformities of this monſter, deſcribed vnto you in all parts, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the verie truth, as it was.</p>
               <p>It reſteth now, that we make vſe of it, and heare what is ſaid in the laſt part of this booke: which containeth in it a chriſtian diſcourſe againſt al vncleanneſſe, and all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane perſons that will not be reformed; with an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation to al others that yet are not ſo defiled in part or in the whole, and to thoſe that haue looked that way, and are deſirous to repent and amende.</p>
               <p>Beloued there be <hi>7.</hi> things, which (as it ſeemeth to me) are the cauſes of all theſe euills in man or woman.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Our Ignorance, that we doe not conſider the end of our creation: which is to glorifie God, by liuing in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to his lawes and commaundements: <hi>Thou ſhalt not not luſt. Thou ſhalt not commit adulterie. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 We forget the end of our calling to the Goſpell, and profeſſion of Ieſus Chriſt: which is, to liue in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe all the dayes of our life.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Thirdly, we looke not into the fruits and effects that are required of vs in Baptiſme: which are, that we ſhould
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:6380:8"/>die to ſinne, and liue to righteouſneſſe: and wherein we doe willingly binde our ſelues to Chriſt, to be his faithfull ſouldiers and ſeruants, to fight againſt ſinne, the world, the fleſh and the diuell, vnder his coullors: which is the Croſſe and afflictions, which he and we that are his, muſt ſuffer of wicked wordlings in this world.</p>
               <p n="4">4 If while we are young, our parents doe not bring vs vp, and keepe vs harde at our booke (if we be of meete degree) nor at our dayly labour and buſineſſe, if we be of meane eſtate: but do ſuffer the one ſort, to haue too much pampering, eaſe, and delicacie: the other, too much Idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, play, and libertie alſo.<note n="*" place="margin">Note</note> And ſathan will worke vpon vs, if we haue but any one of theſe: for true it is, that where God giueth not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gifts of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinencie, or preuenteth by his grace, euery young man after ſixteen or ſeauenteen yeares oulde, and euery mayden of fourteene or fifteene (ſay what they will to the contrarie) hath motion to luſt and fleſhy delights: and the diuell, if it be poſſible, will blowe with the bellowſe of concupiſcence in vs, til y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heate of nature hath ſet both body and ſoule on fire. I will not meddle with naturall Philoſophy in this poynt, nor ſhew you by <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> rule, how you ſhould know this to be true; becauſe they that will giue glorie vnto God, and confeſſe the truth, doe know and finde this true in them ſelues, that I ſay: vnleſſe, as is afore ſhewed, God by his preuenting grace, or with his bleſſed gifte of continency doe goe before them.</p>
               <p n="5">5 A fift reaſon of all this out-rage in the fleſh, is this: that whereas by originall ſinne wee are ſubiect to luſt, and to all other actuall ſinnes (here taking luſt for the ſinnes of vncleanneſſe, and not for all groſſe ſinnes in generall, as the word will affoord) I ſay whereas by ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall guiltynes, we are ſubiect to all ſinne whatſoeuer: ſo are we naturally encliued and deſirous of the means that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:6380:8"/>may further the ſinne that we are moſt enclined vnto: as cloſe companying together, dalyance, ſight, touching, tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king lewdly of the actions of generation, writing of letters, making and reading of lewde and wanton bookes, ballads of loue and pamphlets that tend that way, day &amp; night thoughts; and ſome things, that for modeſty ſake, I neyther can or will name: all which, like ſwine, a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber vſe, without all remorſe of conſcience and the feare of God.</p>
               <p n="6">6 A ſixt reaſon of this outrage is, that wee bee not tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughly made acquainted with Gods boke, and therein ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed day and night (that is to ſay, morning and euening at the leaſt) that ſo we might ſee what God forbids, what he commaunds touching chaſtitie, puritie of body &amp; mind, what puniſhments haue come on men and women, for theſe ſins, and in what acompt God hath them that liue pure, &amp; cleane: of which ſtories, <hi>Gen. 19.</hi> and <hi>38. Iudges 20.2. Sam. 11. Rom. 1.1. Cor. 6. Gal. 5. Ephe. 5. Reue. 20.</hi> &amp; <hi>21.</hi> are wonderfull to conſider.</p>
               <p n="7">7 Our neglect of wiſe &amp; graue hiſtories in this point, &amp; of reading what monſtrous births God hath ſent vnto many both in this Realme, &amp; in other places: which might make vs to tremble and quake, when wee ſhall but reade and heare of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>M. Stubbs,</hi> in his booke entituled <hi>The Anatomie of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes,</hi> doth notably handle this point: ſo doth <hi>M. Hergeſte,</hi> in his booke entituled <hi>The right rule of Chriſtian Chaſtity, M. Batmans</hi> booke, and the <hi>Theater of Gods Iudgment &amp;c.</hi> The which books, I wiſh with all my heart, were dayly heard, &amp; read of our amorous yonkers, &amp; lewde huſwiues of the world, of Courtiers, Citizens, &amp; Countrey people, with all other good like authors.</p>
               <p>Beſides, we ſhould vſe all the good meanes, that might more fully make vs to ſuppreſſe luſt &amp; ſinfull pleaſure: as
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:6380:9"/>to be in good places, godly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church alſo, to heare diuine ſeruice and ſermons &amp;c. Wee doe not giue our ſelues to good exerciſes, that might make vs forget all ſuch matters: as Actiuitie, Studie, reading of the holy and ſacred ſcriptures, Faſting, Praier, Modeſty in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell, Lookes, Geſture, and Countenance &amp;c. But to the contrary, a number haunt whore-houſes, Theatres, and Play-houſes &amp;c. And a number (I am aſhamed to vtter it) are euer talking of lewde howſes, and ſuch filthy places; which through their naughty practiſes they haue founde out and doe knowe: ſo that, as it ſhould ſeeme, the Stues banke was neuer ſo common, as many Allies, Gardens, &amp; ſuch out-places be. Nay, you ſhall heare one young Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant ſay to another; come, and I will bring thee, where thou ſhalt haue a wench of this and that price, &amp;c. Reade I pray you <hi>Thomas Naſhes</hi> booke, entituled; <hi>The teares of Chriſt ouer Ieruſalem:</hi> which booke, if you haue any grace in you, will make you to ſhed teares for your ſinnes: I thinke it is the only beſt booke that euer hee made.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>An inuectiue concluſion.</head>
               <p>O Monſtrous lyfe of men &amp; women, what will feare you, what will amend you? what may make you, if it be but, to ent<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> into ſome good conſideration with your ſelues, of your eſtate before God &amp; man (for this ſin) both in this life, &amp; the life to come? I would to God, I knewe what would doe you good, and preuaile with you: you ſhould not then be long without it. For a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, I am right forrie and full of woe in my heart, when I thinke with my ſelfe how many thouſands are loſt from Chriſt, and caſt to the diuel for theſe and ſuch like ſinnes: as alſo how many are beggerd and vndone thereby in this life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yea, brought into loathſome diſeaſes and griefes, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credit
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:6380:9"/>of parents, kindred, and themſelues for euer, by this ſinne: Inſomuch that the Chronicles and Hiſtories of times are afterwards their perpetuall regiſters of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famie, ſhame and diſcredit.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, to quench thy fierce and furious heate of hott and corrupt nature, let them ſet before them the heate &amp; ſcorching of the euer burning fire of hell; &amp; try but w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> one foote or finger in our ordinarie fire, how they can endure the vnquenchable fire of hell. Then let them but come, and behould one of theſe wanton dames, when ſhe is layed and lyeth rotting of the French diſeaſe (or Poxe as yee tearme it) when one peece is ready to fall from another, and her guts ready to fall out of her belly: when, at the beſt, ſhee is ſlabbering of her ſelfe with her dyet drinkes, her Spaniſh paints, her hot houſe bathes &amp;c. or if that be too too loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, yet let them come to them when they are but ſickly, and doe looke as yellowe as Rites legs, when the ſmall poxe is on them, or when they lie groaning &amp; crying out of inward aches and paines. And let wicked women of all ſorts in this profeſſion, doe the like to their gallants and braue laddes, that haue ſpent themſelues, and all that euer they had on them: &amp; theſe will at the leaſt ſomewhat abate the luſtes and deſires of the fleſh: if not kill it alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither in them. And let them adde hereunto, for breuitie ſake, but that one little booke intituled, <hi>A Chriſtian Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution:</hi> for, that perhaps (if Gods grace be graunted them) will drawe them home to a better life.</p>
               <p>Thus briefely I haue ſhewed my poore opinion, what may be a remedy in part, for this ſinne in a great number, that the diuell may not preuaile with ſo many as he doth in all places: in ſo much, it is counted no ſinne, or but a ſmall ſinne, ſoone wiped away. Nay, would to god y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſome were not growne to ſuch a height of ſinne euery way, as that hauing no other way to ſhift it off, would faine beare
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:6380:10"/>men in hand, that there is no God: ſuch is the ſinfull wickedneſſe of this age and time: God, for his mercies ſake, giue vs all grace to amend. But my maſters, you of the <hi>Macheuillian</hi> and <hi>Atheſt</hi> profeſſion, be you well aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, that if you will not beleeue there is a God, that doth hate ſinne and reward vertue, you ſhall one day finde that, and feele that there is a diuell to plague you &amp; torment you for <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>: therfore looke to it in time, &amp; ſpend not your golden times away in ſuch ſin &amp; dotage as you do. Thus hoping y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> a word is ynough to the wiſe, I end. And, though perhaps this pamphlet may want wiſe handling, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming vnder my hand; I would willingly haue ſhewed at large, what are the particular ſinnes of vncleanneſſe, how they are defined, and the proofes of ſcripture of it: But by reaſon of ſome eſpeciall buſineſſe that to me appertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in my place, and for ſome other reſpects, I am for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced here to conclude; wiſhing, that one or two of theſe bookes (as they are) might be giuen into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hands of the wicked Father and Mother of this monſter; to terrifie them withall, till they doe truely repent: and then I wiſh vnto them all the mercies of god and his Church, with other Chriſtians, according to Saint <hi>Paules rule, 2. Cor. 7.</hi> Otherwiſe, let thoſe, &amp; all other like perſons, feare the ſayings of theſe few places, <hi>1. Cor. 6.9. Reuela. 21.6.7.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Lord Ieſus ſtir vp all that be in authoritie and all other good Chriſtians, to pray, to puniſh, and ſeeke a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe of this and all other groſſe ſinne; that for our iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties we be not ouerthrowne in theſe aged dayes of our moſt gratious Soueraigne Lady, Queene <hi>Elizabeth:</hi> and that the enimies of the Goſpell, nor the great eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of all mankind preuayle not againſt vs, or our children after vs, as we haue deſerued. Amen.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6380:10"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
